So what type of runner are you? Are you a heel striking runner where you
land on your heel and roll through with each stride, or are you a
forefoot striking runner landing on the balls of your feet? In today's
video, I'm going to look at the difference between the two types of
running technique and the a trade off that occurs between those
two different types of footstrike and relate it to your own
injury history. So let's get straight into this. So the important thing
to appreciate is that when it comes to running form, we can't
just change our form and do away with forces at certain
joints and not to consider those forces anymore. It's just like
any type of physics, force can't just be lost.
Instead, it gets moved around and transferred. That's the underpinning principle
to all of this. So whichever way you break it
down, running is a high impact, high load
activity. So whether I'm running with a heel strike, whether I'm running with a forefoot
strike, either way, I have to deal with my body weight coming
down over the top of the landing foot and
the impact that comes back with that, the question is where that
impact goes. So if I'm running with a heel strike,
which so often also comes with a slight overstride, so landing further
in front of myself, then the initial impact that comes back
at my body with that initial contact is
experienced ankle, knee, hip,
up through the kinetic chain, and that initial impact.
A lot of the time runners tend to experience
in terms of knee pain, if injury is
going to start to kick in. So obviously, that's a big generalization.
There are lots of different types of injuries. But in terms of the sorts
of injuries that overstriding, heel striking runners do tend to get
it's things like telephone, real pain. So runners knee, it's things like tibial,
stress fractures, even things like anterior compartment
syndrome around the front of the outside of the Shin. They are classic
kinds of injuries that heel striking runners pick up because
they're the tissues that get overloaded with
this type of heel striking pattern. Now if
we were to move a heel striking runner to more of a forefoot striking pattern,
we know that's going to take a little bit of stress and strain off.
For example, the knee femoral joint, we know that it's going to
put the ankle in a different position, that's initial contact, which means that
the initial eccentric load on muscles like to be asked anterior
are going to be less. So we're less likely to be dealing with things like
anterior compartment syndrome, but we need to
appreciate that force has to go somewhere. So in reducing
the stress on the knee, we end up putting more demand around
the ankle. So our Achilles, our calf complex,
end up working a lot harder to dissipate that initial load.
So we know that with those two different types of running
style. If one is more stressful for
the calf and Achilles complex and the other more stressful around the
knee in particular, Then we can start to make some
sensible decisions based on our individual running injury
histories about how we should potentially start
to think about maybe changing our running style or not,
maybe leaving it alone. Maybe it's nothing to do with your running
style, your injury history, and it's more to do with errors you've made in your
training. But when we're thinking about running style,
if I got someone with knee pain and they're overstriding, Then logic would dictate
that perhaps bringing it to more of a mid foot
to forefoot strike Would help reduce the knee, the stress and
strain around the knee. Whereas if I've got someone who's exactly
the same in as much as the fact that they're overstriding and heel striking
and they're dealing with Achilles problems, they're dealing with pain in their
Achilles tendon or calf problems, Then I probably don't want
to take them and throw them up onto the balls of their feet.
We need to appreciate the way in which those different types
of foot strike Put different stress and strain in different
areas of the body and start to think about where our
own injuries have occurred in the past and if it's appropriate
to perhaps make a subtle change to offload the
previously injured area, or if making a change might put more
stress and strain on that injured area. And that's exactly why
making big changes to your running style is never a good idea.
Making small changes is by far the safest way to go Because
it allows your body within the kind of parameters of what it's used to
just to start to work on making small improvements over time and
adapting as you go, rather than suddenly taking the stress
and strain from one place and moving it to another where perhaps your body is
not ready for that stress and strain to go. In fact, if you want to
learn a little bit more about how to improve your running style when it comes
to your foot strike, then check out the video that I uploaded to the channel
here a few weeks ago which talks about far more detailed
approaches to action actually starting to just improve your foot strike,
make it a little bit more efficient and a little bit better for
you when it comes to running light underfoot, so go check that out.